<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The good and faithful servant set forth in a sermon preached at Hatfield Broad-Oake in Essex, August 2. the day before the funeral of Mr. John Warren, sometime minister of the gospel there. Now published with some small additions, and a brief account of his life and character. By Henry Lukin.</title>
            <author>Lukin, H. (Henry), 1628-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3474A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218826</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830383</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34834</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49461)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34834)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2073:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The good and faithful servant set forth in a sermon preached at Hatfield Broad-Oake in Essex, August 2. the day before the funeral of Mr. John Warren, sometime minister of the gospel there. Now published with some small additions, and a brief account of his life and character. By Henry Lukin.</title>
                  <author>Lukin, H. (Henry), 1628-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst, at the Bible and Three Crowns, the lower end of Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes five advertisement pages.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Warren, John, --  minister of Hatfield Broad Oak, Essex --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34834:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Good and Faithful SERVANT, Set forth in a SERMON Preached at <hi>Hatfield Broad-Oake</hi> in <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex, Auguſt</hi> 2. the day before the Funeral of Mr. <hi>JOHN WARREN,</hi> Sometime Miniſter of the Goſpel there.</p>
            <p>Now Publiſhed with ſome ſmall Additions, and a brief Account of his Life and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter.</p>
            <p>By <hi>HENRY LUKIN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> the lower End of <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:34834:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34834:2"/>
            <head>THE Good and Faithful Servant.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matthew 25.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>His Lord ſaid unto him, Well done, thou good and faithful Servant, thou haſt been faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful over a few things, I will make thee Ruler over many things: enter thou into the joy of thy Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS it was ſaid of the Woman that came with a Box of Ointment of Spikenard, to pour on the head of Jeſus before his Death, She did what ſhe could, ſhe came aforehand to anoint his Body to the Burying; ſhe took the beſt way that ſhe could think of, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs her affection and reſpect to him, <hi>Mark</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 8. So I am come aforehand, anticipating a little the Funeral of our dear Friend, to do what I can to improve ſo ſad a Providence for the benefit of his ſurviving Friends, and to ſpread abroad and preſerve the ſweet ſavour of his Name (which is as a precious Ointment, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.1.) when he is gathered to his Fathers. As un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34834:3"/>the Old Teſtament God multiplied Viſions, and uſed ſimilitudes by the Miniſtry of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.10. So under the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Chriſt ſpake very often to the Multitude in Parables, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.34. This being a very uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful way of teaching. Some call Images Laymens Books, becauſe they ſuppoſe they repreſent things ſo clearly and plainly to the meaneſt capacities; but tho' God is a Spirit, and requires Spiritual Worſhip, yet he hath thought fit to repreſent ſpiritual things by natural; ſo that as it is ſaid, <hi>The inviſible things of him are ſeen clearly from the Creation of the World,</hi> Rom. 1.20. And if we do underſland that of the time ever ſince the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet the words following are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the Works of Creation. But not only the things that are made repreſent to us God's Eternal Power and Godhead, but all things that are done or tranſacted in the World ſerve to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent ſpiritual things to us: And while we have ſuch a Teacher as Chriſt to inſtruct us in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance that is betwixt theſe things; they may be of much uſe to us to help our underſtandings and memories, to quicken our affections, and to invite and draw our thoughts to heavenly things; ſo as we can hardly be about any worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but we may take occaſion from thence to raiſe up our minds to heavenly things; which is a great advantage to us, becauſe we have ſo little command over our thoughts, and becauſe all our actions have their firſt riſe from our thoughts; out of the heart proceed firſt evil thoughts, and thence murders, adulteries, fornications, <hi>&amp;c. Matth.</hi> 15.19.</p>
            <p>Before I proceed further, I will premiſe that in ſimilitudes the Scripture is very brief and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34834:3"/>conciſe, ſo that there is not only an omiſſion ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of the note of ſimilitude (which doth fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently occur in Scripture) but the <hi>Protaſis</hi> and <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> as they are called, are confounded toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not ſet exactly one againſt another, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained one by the other, as <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.22. A fair Woman is not as a Jewel of Gold, but Beauty in a fooliſh Woman, as a Jewel of Gold in a Swines ſnout: So <hi>John</hi> 3.8. He that is born of the Spirit, is not like the Wind, but in the buſineſs of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, the Spirit works freely, inviſibly; yet ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually as the Wind blows. Sometimes that only which belongs to the <hi>Protaſis</hi> or former part of the ſimilitude is expreſſed without that in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the ſimilitude which anſwers thereto, as <hi>Luke</hi> 12.35. <hi>Let your loins be girded about, and your lights burning.</hi> We need not buſie our ſelves to find out what are theſe loins that ſhould be girt, and thoſe lights that ſhould be burning, for thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions belong to the perſons that we ſhould be like to: As thoſe that wait for their Maſter's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a Wedding, ſhould not only be up and have their Cloths on, but ſhould have thoſe Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments girded about them, (which were much like Morning Gowns) which they could not well ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther run in, or do ſervice in, unleſs they were girt about them, as you may ſee by 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.46. and <hi>Luke</hi> 17.8. So they ſhould not only have their lights or lamps by them, but have them ready lighted, that they might not make their Maſters ſtay when they knocked, till they were prepared to wait on them; but that they might open to them immediately: So we ſhould not only be in a <hi>Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> preparation for Death, by being in a ſtate of Grace; but in an <hi>Actual</hi> preparation for it, having our Evidences for Heaven ready, our hearts
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34834:4"/>weaned from the World, a clear proſpect of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Glory, and being always ſo employed, as Death may not ſurprize us idle, or doing that which is evil. I have ſpent ſo many words on this thing, becauſe it may be of uſe to us for the right underſtanding of this Parable, out of which the words of the Text are taken, wherein he inſtructs his Diſciples how they thould carry themſelves in his abſence; the time of his Departure from them being now at hand. We have this Parable differently ſet down here, and in <hi>Lu.</hi> 19.12. For it is here in the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> as it is in the Books of <hi>Samuel, Kings</hi> and <hi>Chronicles</hi> in the Old Teſtament; what is omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in one Book, is ſet down in another; ſo that put together, they make the Hiſtory more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat; therefore the Greek Tranſlators of the Old Teſtament call the Books of <hi>Chronicles, Parali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pomena,</hi> or praetermiſſions, becauſe many things are added in them, which were omitted in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Books. In <hi>Luke</hi> he plainiy foretells what he ſhould meet with from the Jews, and how he ſhould be rejected of them: But in both he is compared to one going from home, and leaving his Servants. <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith a Noble man going to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Kingdom: He muſt indeed be a great Man that gave ſo many Talents to his Servants to Trade with, till he came back again. The Parable plainly ſhews that he gave to ſome more, to ſome leſs, according to their places and abilities. <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith, Pounds, but the Evangeliſts have regard ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the ſenſe and meaning of Chriſt, than to his words; they both imply that he gave different ſumms of money, or portions of goods: Now when they come to give an account of the improvement of what he had committed to their truſt, the firſt had doubled his Stock, or what he was truſted
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34834:4"/>withal; and here in the Text we have his Lords approbation of what he had done, and his liberal rewarding of his diligence and faithfulneſs. It was but little in compariſon which he had truſted him with, but he ſhould be Ruler over much; as he that had been faithful in the adminiſtration of the Affairs of the Houſhold, ſhould be made Steward of all his Maſters Eſtate, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.47 In <hi>Luke</hi> it is, <hi>Have thou Authority over ten Cities;</hi> having reſpect, as I ſaid before, rather to the meaning of Chriſt, than to his words, and therein it is likely he alludes to the Honour wherewith Princes or Conquerours uſe to recompence the ſignal and eminent ſervice of thoſe that have acquitted themſelves well under them, preferring them to the Govenment of ſome great Places or Cities, and ſuch an one ſhould have Rule over many Cities; ſtill obſerve that theſe expreſſions have reſpect to the <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or former part of the ſimilitude.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As for thoſe words, <hi>Enter thou into the Joy of thy Lord,</hi> if they be referred to the <hi>Protaſis,</hi> they only ſignifie that he ſhould enter upon or take poſſeſſion of that honour or preferment which he ſhould promote him to, or delight to confer upon him, as <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> would know what ſhould be done unto the man to whom the King delighted to honour, <hi>Eſt.</hi> 6.6. I come now to the ſpiritual mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Parable, or that which is hereby ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Now it is agreed on by all that the ſcope of the Parable is to ſhew, That Chriſt being gone to Heaven, hath given variety of gifts to men, which they are to improve for him in his ſervice for his glory, which he will require an account of when he comes to Judgment. Men have from this Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble learned to call them <hi>Talents</hi> in their ordinary ſpeech, but in ſtrictneſs they might as well have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34834:5"/>them <hi>Pounds</hi> from the Parallel place in <hi>Luke,</hi> yet I diſlike not the uſe of the word in this caſe, becauſe it is not ſo common a word as pound, nor uſed in ſo many caſes, and the uſe of this word may put men in mind of the end and uſe of thoſe various gifts which they have received. Now by theſe gifts we do not underſtand only thoſe gifts which he gave unto men at his Aſcenſion, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8. The various kinds whereof the Apoſtle mentions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4, &amp;c. but thoſe manifold gifts of God, or graces which are but gifts freely given, as they are called, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10. whereby we are capable or qualified to do good to others or ſervice to God. The Philoſophers uſe to diſtinguiſh them into the goods of the body, of the mind, and of fortune. By the goods of the body they mean, Health, Strength, outward Senſe, as, Seeing, Hearing, and a good Temper or Conſtitution, ſo as it may be moſt ſerviceable to the mind. The Goods of the Mind are ſuch as quickneſs of apprehenſion, good Judgment, a firm and faithful Memory, Learning, Knowledge; by the Goods of Fortune they mean, Riches, Honour, Authority, Intereſt. Now tho' we do not approve of their calling them the Goods of Fortune, [<hi>Auſtin</hi> was not pleaſed that he had ſo oft-uſed that word, yet ſhews in what ſenſe it may be uſed, <hi>Retractat. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.] yet by what I have ſaid we may ſee under what general Heads we may reduce thoſe various gifts which are committed to our truſt; and I will now ſhew you,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That we receive all theſe from God; and theſe things may indifferently be ſaid to be given by God the Father, or by Jeſus Chriſt, as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour. For all power is Originally from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34834:5"/>to whom it muſt be again reſigned, when Chriſt hath fulfilled his Mediatory Office, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But in the mean while all power in Heaven and Earth is committed to Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.16. for the good of his Church, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.22. and in order to their Salvation, <hi>John</hi> 17.2. Now it is God that giveth to all, Life, and Breath, and all things, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.25. It is he that did form and faſhion us in the Womb, and did not fail of mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any one part of the body, but did faſhion us as perfectly as if he had a model or a receit in a Book to make us by, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 139.16. And as the Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mixes his Colours ſo as to give the right com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion to a picture; God doth ſo temper the ſeveral humours of the body as they way be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the mind in ſuch manner and meaſure as he pleaſes, and hence proceeds the different temper of men whereby they are fitted for ſeveral buſineſſes and employments: and it is God that makes to differ even in our natural Temper and Conſtitution; If there be in one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or any good natural Inclination, and in another ſuch an ill Temper, as <hi>Socrates</hi> acknowledged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to have it is God that makes the difference; and hence it is that one hath quickneſs of appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and preſence of Mind, another ſolidity of Judgment, another a curious Fancy, another a ſtrong Memory; and hereby they are fitted and qualified for Buſineſs and ſeveral Employments. So thoſe that they call the Goods of Fortune are from God, who gives us all things richly to enjoy, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17, &amp;c. Both Riches and Honour come of him, and in his hand it is to make great and to give ſtrength to all, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.12. It is God that gives us all things pertaining to life and godlineſs, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. So that we have nothing but what we have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:34834:6"/>
            <p>Seondly, We are but Stewards of theſe manifold gifts of God, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 4.10. Thoſe words of the Apoſtle may have reſpect both to what goeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and what followeth after; We are not only to Miniſter of our Subſtance with thoſe good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.3. But of thoſe ſpiritual gifts which we have received, as we have occaſion and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity: he that is Steward to another, if he have any thing of his own, may imploy it as he ſees good, but thoſe things which belong to him, that he is a Steward for, he muſt improve for his advantage; or he that is Factor for another muſt Trade with what he hath ſent to him, for the beſt advantage of him that truſts him, and muſt not let his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney or ſtock lye dead; and there will a time come that we muſt be called to a reckoning, and have that Summons ſent to us, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.2. <hi>Come give an account of your Stewardſhip, for you muſt be no longer Stewards.</hi> Now therefore we ſhould conſider what we have committed to our truſt; they that have moſt have but little in compariſon, as it is ſaid to him here that had the five Talents, that he had been faithul in a few things: As it is ſaid of thoſe extraordinary gifts which they had in the primitive times; to one was given the word of Wiſdom, to another the word of Knowledge, to another Faith, to another the gifts of Healing, to another working of miracles, to another Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8, 9, 10. So now, ſome have Health and Strength; ſome abilities of Mind, ſome Riches, ſome Power and Authority, ſome Intereſt in great Perſons whereby they may obtain favours for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; now we ſhould (as it is ſaid, <hi>The Liberal man deviſes Liberal things, Iſa.</hi> 32.18.) caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout what we ſhould do with what we have in our power, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Silver and Gold have I none,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34834:6"/>but ſuch as I have I give thee,</hi> Acts 3.6. Some now have Silver and Gold, tho' they have not the gift of Healing; Some, tho they have neither of theſe, are capable of doing good ſome other way: The Prophet was inquiſitive what he ſhould do for the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> and he would know whether ſhe would be ſpoken for to the King or the Captain of the Hoſt; by reaſon of the Miracles which he wrought, he had an Intereſt in them, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.13. <hi>Job</hi> had ſeveral Talents (as we ſpeak) committed to him, he was a great man, he had Riches, Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Intereſt, Wiſdom and Underſtanding, and he improved them, ſo that when the Ear heard him, it bleſſed him, and when the eye ſaw him, it gave witneſs to him, he delivered the poor that cried, and the fatherleſs and him that had none to help him; the bleſſing of him that was ready to periſh came upon him, and he cauſed the widows heart to ſing for Joy. This he might do by his Authority and Intereſt; by his Riches he was eyes to the blind and feet to the lame; either taking care of thoſe who were really ſo, to make a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to the defect of their ſenſes or limbs, or he was a guide to the ignorant, directing and counſelling them in thoſe things which they had not an inſight into, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.19. and ſupporting them when they were ready to fall, or to be caſt down by others; By his Wiſdom he ſearched out the cauſe which he knew not, and by his Authority he brake the Jaws of the Wicked, and plucked the ſpoil out of his teeth, <hi>Job</hi> 29.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is, he reſcued the prey from them, alluding to Dogs or ravenous Creatures that muſt ſometimes have their teeth broken to prevent their doing miſchief, or to get the prey out of their mouth, ſee <hi>Pſa.</hi> 3.7. and 58.6. One had five Talents committed to him, another
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34834:7"/>two, another one: So we may not have ſo much committed to our truſt as <hi>Job</hi> had, yet ſomething we may have whereby we may ſerve Chriſt, and do good to others; we may, if we have Riches, relieve others in their ſtraits, diſperſe Bibles and good Books, encourage and promote the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel, and ſo be helpers with the Miniſters of the Goſpel in the work of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.3. If God have given us knowledge, we may inſtruct others in our ſeveral Relations and Capacities; as Husbands, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. as Parents, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.8.6.20. as Chriſtian Friends inſtructing others in ſome things, who in other things may know more than our ſelves, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.23. If we have any intereſt in others, we have the greater advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for doing them good, as we have the greater obligation thereto.</p>
            <p>I come now to ſpeak of the favour they ſhall find with God, and the reward which they ſhall receive from him, that have well improved their Gifts; <hi>Well done good and faithful ſervant,</hi> then ſhall every man have praiſe of God, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. That is, all that have praiſe: Men muſt not then put in to paſs their cenſures, but we ſhall depend upon God, for our final Sentence, which ſhall determine our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal State. But what are we! that God ſhould ſhew us ſuch favour, or what are our Services that he ſhould approve of them? we muſt ſay as <hi>David</hi> in another caſe, 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.14, 16. Of thine own have we given thee, all this Store cometh of thine hand, and is all thine own; So we are nothing, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. And whatever we have done, it is not we, but the Grace of God, which is with us, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. If God promiſe any favour to any Grace, or to any Perſon qualified therewith: As to thoſe that fear him, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. To thoſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34834:7"/>that love him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. He doth not therein ſhow the reaſon of his beſtowing ſuch favours, but the order in which he be ſtows them: It is he that puts his fear into our hearts, and circumciſes our hearts to love him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. <hi>Deu.</hi> 30.6. And in this reſpect we may be ſaid to receive grace for grace. I have before ſhewed you what the literal meaning of thoſe words may be, <hi>I will make thee Ruler over many things.</hi> And doubtleſs the ſcope of the Parable is to ſhew how liberally and bountifully God will recompence any Service which is done for him above our deſert.</p>
            <p>Thoſe words, <hi>Enter thou into the joy of thy Lord;</hi> expreſs more particularly what ſhall be done to thoſe whom God doth delight to honour. An en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance ſhall be miniſtred to them abundantly, into the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. The Scriptures do not diſtinguiſh ſo critically as the Philoſophers, who call ſenſual delights, <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> and intellectual or Spiritual delight, <hi>Joy,</hi> for according to the Scripture there is in the preſence of God, fulneſs of Joy and Pleaſures for evermore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. Now the joy of our Lord may be either that joy which we have from him, as the praiſe of God, is that praiſe which we have from God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.43. Or it may be that joy which our Lord himſelf hath or is entered into; for He, for the joy that was ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him, endured the Croſs, and deſpiſed the ſhame, <hi>Hebrews</hi> 12.2.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay it is that joy which we have from God, and this is enough to commend it to us, and raiſe up our minds to great expectations of it: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſhuerus</hi> called in help to contrive what ſhould be done to the man whom the King delighted to honour, <hi>Esth.</hi> 6.6. and the faithful Servants of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34834:8"/>Chriſt are ſuch as God doth delight to honour; and as <hi>Ahaſhuerus</hi> in the feaſt that he made for his Nobles and Princes, would ſhew both his favour to them, and the riches of his glorious Kingdom, and the honour of his excellent Majeſty, and ſo gave them drink in Veſſels of Gold diverſe one from another (it is likely of different faſhions) and royal Wine in abundance, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 1.4, 7. So God will ſhew the riches of his Glory on the Veſſels of mercy which he had afore prepared unto glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.23. as he will ſhew the riches of his grace in his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards us in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.7. As it is ſaid, <hi>Araunah</hi> gave as a King to <hi>David</hi> in reſpect of his bounty and munificence, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.23. ſo God will be a God to his People, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. dealing as a God with them in magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence and munificence; and as none knows the power of his Anger, which is according to his fear, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.11. ſo none knows the riches of his Glory, which is according to our moſt raiſed hopes and expectations, yea far exceeding them; as the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> found the Glory of <hi>Solomon</hi> far to exceed the report of it in her own Country, tho' that report was above her belief, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.67. Chriſt and Heaven ſuffer no <hi>Hyperbole,</hi> nothing too great can be ſaid of them: God needs not to take counſel of any to know what ſhall be done to thoſe whom he delights to honour; that manifold Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which could find out a way to ſave Sinners without any injury to his Law or Juſtice, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.10. can prepare that happineſs for them, which will make him to be glorified in his Saints, and admired in all thoſe that believe 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. There are two ways whereby we may make ſome conjecture at the Joy of Heaven. Firſt, By the Joy or Pleaſure which we ſee men take in theſe worldly ſenſitive
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34834:8"/>Objects, when there is an innate inſtinct, deſire, appetite and ſenſes ſuited to that goodneſs which is in any Creature, then it is to us as the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to the Iron, which draws it to it. We could not enjoy the fragrant ſcent of a Flower without the fence of ſmelling; and thoſe that want that ſence, may well wonder what it is that makes men delight ſo much in ſweet ſmells; and (to uſe a plain ſimilitude) if ſuch an one were to buy but a pair of Gloves, they would obſerve the matter of them, the faſhion or making of them, and the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of them, but they could not value them for their rich perfume, which doth ſo much enhance or raiſe the price of them: So others are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranced in Pleaſure, by the raviſhing melody of Muſick, which is nothing to thoſe that want the fence of hearing; and ſo the moſt charming Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are nothing to thoſe that want the fence of ſeeing, or where deſire fails, as the wiſe man ſpeaks, through the decays of Nature and declining Age, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.5. But all the Glory of this World is no more to the Joy of our Lord, than the Husks which the Swine fed upon was to the Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which the Prodigal had in his Father's houſe, there we ſhall have the moſt excellent Objects, and we ſhall perfectly enjoy them, when our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings are perfectly enlightened to know what is the Riches of the Glory of his Inheritance in the Saints, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.18. and our affections perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed ſo as to follow hard after God, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 63.8. as one ſaid, not <hi>panis Domini,</hi> but <hi>panis Dominus,</hi> ſo there will be not only <hi>Gaudium Domini,</hi> the joy of the Lord, but <hi>Gaudium Dominus,</hi> the Lord our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding joy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 43.4. and there will not be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Glory prepared for us, but we ſhall be prepared for Glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.23. we ſhall be made meet to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34834:9"/>be partakers of an Inheritance with the Saints in light, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12. There were two things which made <hi>Solomon</hi> a competent Judge of what was to be found in theſe Earthly things, His Riches, whereby he was able to purchaſe or procure the beſt of what this world could afford, and his Wiſdom, whereby he was able both to draw out the quinteſſence or vertue of every thing and to make a Critical Judgment of it, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.1,—9. So in Heaven there will be the moſt excellent Objects, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaid a little before his death; that place, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.22, &amp;c. did deſerve a thouſand thouſand thoughts, there we ſhall ſee God as he is, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. We ſhall be fit to be admitted into that general Aſſembly, and to joyn with them in that Divine ſervice wherein they ſerve him day and night, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.15. without ſaying, What a wearineſs is it, our hearts will be fixed to ſing and give praiſe, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 108.1. We ſtrive ſometimes to wind them up to make melody to the Lord, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. but as when a Lute or Viol is tuned, the pegs will looſen and the ſtrings ſlacken and ſpoil the melody; ſo when we would lift up our hearts to God, they ſink down again, but they will not only be <hi>prepared</hi> but <hi>fixed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, We may make ſome conjecture at this joy by the fore-taſts which we have of it here, where we walk by faith and not by ſight, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. but tho' we ſee him not, yet believing we rejoyce (with joy unſpeakable, and full of Glory, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. It is that which we cannot expreſs, and is full of Glory, as that power where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a Chriſtian is ſtrengthened to all patience and long-ſuffering with joyfulneſs, enabling him to bear long affliction with joyfulneſs is a glorious power, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.11. If we may be filled with all joy and peace
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34834:9"/>in believing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13. what will it be to ſee, as we are ſeen? If theſe are ſuch ſtrong conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that ſome drops of them will revive our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Spirits in the greateſt afflictions, 2. <hi>Cor. chap.</hi> 8.2. what will it be to drink of the River of his pleaſures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.8. when we ſhall have no affliction to allay the ſweetneſs of it? The joy that Chriſtians have had here, hath been ſometimes as much as they could bear, but here we are but as perſons which begin to recover their health, and ſo find ſome ſavour and reliſh in what they eat and drink, but in Heaven we ſhall be as thoſe, that having more fully recovered their health and appetite, take pleaſure in eating and drinking, and taſte the ſweetneſs of their meat and drink. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as I told you, it is the joy of our Lord, or that which was ſet before him to encourage him againſt his ſufferings, and he will not only come again and receive us to himſelf, that where he is we may be alſo, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.3. that we may behold the Glory which the Father hath given him, but he gives the ſame Glory to them which the Father hath given him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.22.24. as they ſuffer with him, ſo they ſhall be glorified together, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17, 18. To him that overcomes, Chriſt will grant to ſit with him in his Throne, as he alſo overcame, and is ſet down with his Father in his Throne, <hi>Rev. Chap.</hi> 3.21. We have a glimpſe of this Glory, in the transfiguration of Chriſt, <hi>Matt.</hi> 17.2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> his face did ſhine as the Sun, and his whole body was ſo illuſtrious, that it darted a brightneſs through his garments, and there were two of the general Aſſembly with him; <hi>Peter</hi> was ſo taken with it, that he thought it was good for them to be there, but this continued only a little while, it is liketheir joy was allaid by the diſcourſe about his deceaſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34834:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:34834:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:34834:11"/>which he ſhould accompliſh at <hi>Jeruſalem, Lu.</hi> 9.31. but now this is already accompliſhed; He hath ſuffered &amp; isentered into his glory, &amp; we ſhall go &amp; bewith him which is far better than to be here, <hi>Phi.</hi> 1.23.</p>
            <p>For the Application of this, let us obſerve and conſider what we have received; formerly in the Apoſtles times, all were not Apoſtles, nor all Prohpers, nor all Teachers, nor all workers of Miracles, all had not the Gift of healing, all did not ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k with Tongues nor all Intepret, 1. <hi>Cor. Chap.</hi> 12.29, 30. So now all have not Riches, Power, Intereſt, Learning, Wiſdom: But every one hath ſomething, wherewith he may ſome way promote the Service and Intereſt of Chriſt, and do good to others When the Tabernacle was made <hi>Bezaleel</hi> was filled with the Spirit of God in wiſdom, in underſtanding, in knowledge, and in all manner of Workmanſhip, to deviſecunning works, to work in Gold, Silver and Braſs, <hi>Exod. Chap.</hi> 31.2, 3. But the Women alſo that were wiſe hearted did Spin with their hands, and brought that which they had Spun of blue, purple, ſcarlet and fine Linnen, <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.25. <hi>Paul</hi> was as a wife Maſter-builder, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10. but <hi>Aquilla</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> Tent makers, were his helpers in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16 3. and there were Women which laboured with him in the Goſpel, <hi>Phil. c.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 3, not by Preaching, but by Teaching good things to younger perſons, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.3. to their Children, which is a great help to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and ſuch as are more fit to hear the Word with profit (as Petty Schools fit Children for Grammar Schools) ſo they may relieve, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, protect ſuch as are capable of doing other ſervice, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.4. and hereby we may be fellow-helpers to the Truth, 3 <hi>John v.</hi> 8.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34834:11"/>And Miniſters could do little in City or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in propagating the Goſpel, if they had not others to help with them: As <hi>the liberal man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes liberal things,</hi> Iſa. 32.8. ſo we ſhould deviſe and caſt about what we may do any way, or in any capacity for the furtherance of the work of Chriſt: We ſhould not only honour the Lord with our ſubſtance, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.9. but we ſhould ſay in truth to him, what is ordinarily ſaid in complement to others, that all that we have is at his ſervice; as all things are of him, ſo it is fit all things ſhould be to him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. As it is ſaid, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.6. <hi>In the hearts of all that are wiſe-hearted, I have put wiſdom, that they may make all that I have commanded th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> What any have is from God, and it is that they may imploy it in his ſervice. He that had but one Talent, was puniſhed becauſe he did not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it; he did not ſpend it as the Prodigal did his Portion among Harlots, or in riotous living, but hid it in the Earth, and returned it to him again, <hi>Match,</hi> 25. <hi>verſe</hi> 25. It is not enough that we do not embezel our Lord's goods, or that we do no hurt therewith; as it is ſaid, <hi>Celata virtus paulo diſtat abinertiâ,</hi> unknown or conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Virtue differs little from ignorance, or idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and I do not account it much to a man's praiſe, to have it ſaid of him, that he is a <hi>Man of unknown worth.</hi> It is true, ſometimes as folly is ſet in great dignity, ſo the Rich ſit in low place, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.6. Where the oppoſition teaches us to underſtand it of thoſe that are Rich in Virtue, Wiſdom, Noble Endowments; this is an evil under the Sun, and an Errour that proceeds from Princes, not to advance men according to their worth, and in ſuch a caſe men
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34834:12"/>have not occaſion or opportunity for putting forth themſeles, or ſhewing what is in them. If ſome very Learned man were confined to ſome obſcure Country Village, he would not have much occaſion to ſhew his Learning; or if a man have Prudence, Courage, Conduct to qualifie him for ſerving his King and Country in Councel or Camp, but by Law is made uncapable thereof, he may be as a lighted Candle under a Buſhel, and ſometimes again a mans modeſty may over awe him that he doth not put forth himſelf, which is better than boaſting of a falſe gift, <hi>Pro.</hi> 25.14. or through vain glory to take all occaſions to make oſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our own worth or ability, trading for our ſelves with our Lords gifts, as <hi>Gehazi</hi> that would get ſomething by the Cure which was wrought on <hi>Naaman,</hi> 2 Kings 5.20. We muſt take heed of thinking the ſervice loſt that we do for God, wherein we do not pocket up ſome applauſe or praiſe for our ſelves. Remember the Leproſie that cleaved to <hi>Gehazi,</hi> and the end of <hi>Herod</hi> that gave not glory to God, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.23. Thoſe that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter muſt do it, as of the Ability which God gives them, that God in all things may be glorified, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11. We muſt not do as <hi>Iſrael</hi> that truſted in her beauty, and plaid the Harlot becauſe of her renown; for that beauty which was perfect through that comlineſs which God had put upon her, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.14. But on the other hand we muſt not through a ſly and ſecret pride refuſe to trade becauſe we have but one Talent, or to put forth our ſelves, becauſe we have no more to make ſhew of; there is a good ſenſe of that, <hi>ſcire tuum nihil eſt niſi te ſcire hoc ſciat alter,</hi> what thou knoweſt is nothing unleſs others know that thou knoweſt it, for we have not received it for our ſelves, as the manifeſtation of the Spirit is given
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34834:12"/>to every man to profit withal, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. and as the ruſt of ſilver and gold will be a witneſs againſt thoſe that have treaſured it up, <hi>James</hi> 5.3. So the hiding of mens gifts, that is, not improving them, will be charged upon them. But what then will the end of thoſe be that abuſe their gifts? in this Caſe, he that is not with Chriſt is againſt him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.30. becauſe he hath received his gifts to imploy and improve in his ſervice, as he that is liſted in a Princes ſervice, and receives his pay, is againſt him, if he ſtand neuter or does nothing, much more if he fights againſt him. If God give a man Riches, and he make uſe of them to oppreſs the poor, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.6. or to make proviſion for the Fleſh to fill the luſts thereof, <hi>Rom</hi> 13.14. ſpending it on Pride or Voluptuouſneſs: If God have given men Power or Intereſt, that is, if they either be in Authority themſelves, or can make an Intereſt in ſuch as are ſo, and take advantage thereby to cruſh the Fatherleſs or the poor; it is that which <hi>Job</hi> durſt not do, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction from God was a terrour to him, and by reaſon of his highneſs he could not endure, <hi>Job</hi> 31.23. If God give a man Learning and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and he ſet himſelf therewith to oppoſe the Truth and Cauſe of Chriſt, and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and ſupport an evil Cauſe againſt Chriſt; If be give a man quickneſs of wit and parts, and he make uſe of it to ridicule Religion, and expoſe thoſe that are moſt ſtrict and conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the profeſſion of it, or to defraud and over-reach his Neighbour; If he give a man ſtrength and ability of body which he might have uſed to good purpoſes in the ſervice of God or of his Country, and he ſpend his ſtrength in Luxury and debauchery, <hi>Pro.</hi> 5.11,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34834:13"/>23, 29. We may ask them as <hi>Cyprian</hi> doth thoſe that uſed Painting and ſuch Arts, how they can look upon God, when they are not as he made them, but as their own luſts have deformed them: This is like taking the Corn and Wine, and Oyl, and Silver, and Gold, which God had given to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and preparing it for <hi>Baal</hi> an abominable Idol, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.8. And if the unprofitable Servant that hid his Talent ſhall be caſt into outer Darkneſs; ſure the wicked Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant that abuſes his Talent to the diſ-ſervice and diſ-honour of God ſhall have Hell made, as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s fiery Furnace, ſeven times more hot than it was wont to be, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.19. In this caſe there is not only <hi>lucrum ceſſans,</hi> but <hi>damnum emergens,</hi> not only a loſs of what night have been gained by a good improvement of what men are truſted with, but a further dan age accrewing by miſimploying of their Talent: As if a Perſon ſhould leave a Steward to look to the affairs of his houſhold, and leave him money to buy and make an advantage for his Maſter, and he ſhould with his money Drink, and Game, and keep Company ſo as to neglect his Maſters buſineſs, and let that ſuffer for want of looking after. Or, as if a man ſhould be at charge to bring up his Son in the ſtudy of the Law, that he might get an Eſtate and be a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and ornament to his Family, and when he hath attained ſome skill in the Law, inſtead of getting an Eſtate thereby, ſhould uſe it only to winde himſelf into his Fathers Eſtate and cheat him of it. Rules are made more plain by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, therefore I ſhall to illuſtrate what I have ſpoken, give an inſtance of a <hi>good and faithful Servant</hi> in him, whoſe death hath given occaſion of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34834:13"/>the foregoing diſcourſe: I do not intend to give an account of his Life, but only to give a brief account of ſome things which may ſhew what Talents he was truſted with, and what uſe he made of them. God who preſides over our forming in the womb (as I have already ſhewed) gave him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Temperamenti,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ingenij,</hi> a good <hi>Craſis</hi> or conſtitution of body, and a good temper of mind both of which did much fit him for the work which he was called to. He had ſomewhat a deep tincture of melancholy, yet not ſuch as to dull or cloud his mind, but rather to poiſe it, and ſo tempered as he had both a quick apprehenſion, and ſolid judgement; He had ſo much of it as to make him ſuſpicious, and cautious of obtruding any crude or indigeſted notions on others, and it will be found as ſoon as any of his labours are made publique, (which an exceſs of modeſty hath hitherto kept from the view of the world) that they do <hi>Demorſos ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere ungues,</hi> according to the advice of the Poet, <hi>ſaepe ſtylum vertas iterum quae digna legi ſint Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus,</hi> well weighing and conſidering what ever proceeded from him; He entered early indeed on the work of the Miniſtry, but he was not more apt to teach, than apt for teaching: He was none of thoſe that <hi>Beza</hi> ſpeaks of, which are <hi>Doctores,</hi> but <hi>Aptiores ad ſtivam,</hi> fitter for the Plow, than for teaching: While young, he was not only a <hi>Titular</hi> but <hi>real Maſter of Arts;</hi> when Mr. Vines (a competent Judge of mens abilities) heard him preach, he ſaid, He looked like a Boy, but ſpake like a Man: He came to <hi>London</hi> in forty two, and did deſign to go beyond Sea with ſome Merchants, but meeting occaſionally with Sir <hi>Thomas Barrington,</hi> he was ſo pleaſed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34834:14"/>with his Converſe, that he prevailed with him to go to <hi>Hatfield</hi> in the begnning of forty three; their <hi>Lecturer</hi> being newly dead, whom he ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in that place, when he was but in the two and twentieth year of his age, being born on <hi>September</hi> 29th one thouſand ſix hundred twenty one. There he continued till he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced away, and though he had invitations to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral more publique places, where he might have had far greater worldly advantage, I heard him ſay above fifty years ago, that he would not leave <hi>Hatfield</hi>-Chriſtians for any place in <hi>England;</hi> There being then many Eminent Chriſtians, moſt of which are long ſince admitted into the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Aſſembly amongſt he Spirits of juſt men made perfect, whither he is now gone to them. At his firſt coming thither, he only preached the weekly Lecture, (which had continued there many years) and on the Sabbath daies in the afternoon, but after ſome time the Miniſter of the place having another Living in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> was obliged to reſide there and quit <hi>Hatfield,</hi> and then the whole work did devolve upon Mr. <hi>Warten;</hi> So that he preached conſtantly three times a week at home, and took his turn in ſeveral other Lectures, which were kept by a Combination of Miniſters; Yet his frequent Preaching did not make him ſlight therein, his Lecture was frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by many of the Neighbouring Miniſters, his Sermons were chiefly deſigned and accommodated to the uſe of ſerious experienced Chriſtians, of which there were many then; his Sermons were not as ſome things which are <hi>Compoſitions</hi> indeed, wherein ſeveral things are put together, and the ingredients appear in groſs lumps; and they do not incorporate together, and ſo the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34834:14"/>virtue of them is loſt, whereas when they are well mixed they do not ſo obviouſly appear, but there is the virtue of them. So learning doth little good in Sermons, where it appears in long quotations, School terms and diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, exotick or foreign words; but then it doth moſt good in Sermons when Miniſters make uſe of it to inſinuate or work things ſo into the affections of their hearers, that they may e're they are aware be made as the Charets of <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadab, Cant.</hi> 6.12. or come upon them with that power and evidence of Truth, that they may not be able to withſtand the wiſdom and ſpirit wherewith they ſpeak, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.10. But beſides this ordinary work, there were then monthly Faſts, which he uſually kept without the help of others; wherein he did not hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle over the duties of the day in compliance with the weakneſs of thoſe that ſay of ſuch days as the <hi>Jews</hi> of their new Moons and Sabbaths, when will they be gone? <hi>Amos</hi> 8.5. And of the duties thereof, <hi>what a wearineſs is it? Mal. ch.</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 13. But he kept them with Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as days of afflicting the ſoul, and with ſuch fervency and perſeverance in prayer as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Nation did then require: And beſides theſe his aſſiſtants was frequently deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in days of Solemn prayer and humiliation, on particular occaſions, he being an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> indeed, not only as without guile, but as one that had power with God in prayer, and did oft prevail; for which reaſon I have ſeveral times been deſired by Chriſtians to engage Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> to pray for them, and have ſince his death received Letters from ſome lamenting the loſs of ſuch a praying Friend, and he hath oft
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34834:15"/>put me in mind of the words of Mr. <hi>Welſh</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning an eminent Chriſtian in <hi>Scotland:</hi> Happy is that City, yea happy is that Nation, that hath an <hi>Hugh Kennedy;</hi> and adds (what I may truly ſay concerning Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> I have my ſelf certainly found the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers of his prayers from the Lord in my behalf.</p>
            <p>And beſides all this, there was a monthly Meeting of ſome Miniſters, which he was the firſt promoter of, that continued many years, wherein there were Diſputations and Latine Sermons, wherein I have oft heard Poſitions, and Determinations, which might well have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Divinity-Schools, or have entertained an Academical Auditory. All theſe things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired much ſtudy, which he had need be a good Husband to find time for, amidſt ſo much buſineſs, eſpecially conſidering how much Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance and Company he had; all that knew him, being ſo deſirous of his Converſation, which was ſo pleaſing and profitable, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny having recourſe to him for ſatisfying their doubts, he having (according to the Proverb) an Eagle's Eye, and a Lady's Hand, in dealing with wounded Conſciences; that is, a deep and piercing in ſight into matters of that nature, and much of tenderneſs and compaſſion towards ſuch perſons. And further (as was obſerved of Mr. <hi>Joſeph Mede,</hi> that profound Scholar, that he ſeemed moſt delighted with thoſe Studies which might ſtrain the ſinews of his Brain, and therefore did ſet upon the moſt difficult places of Scripture ſo.) Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> did Preach long upon the <hi>Song of Solomon,</hi> and the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> As that pious learned judicious Man Mr. <hi>Durham</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> likewiſe did, though Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> did not undertake to determine any
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34834:15"/>thing upon the Prophetical part of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi> I know thoſe are charged with arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance and over-weening, that will attempt to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain ſuch difficult places of Scripture; yet there is a bleſſing promiſed to him that reads, and to him that hears the words of the <hi>Revelation, Chap.</hi> 1.3. There are many things therein that muſt be kept, and therefore underſtood; and certainly there are many things in both theſe Books that at firſt ſeem very obſcure, which (by prayer, ſtudy, and comparing them with other places of Scripture) may be made more plain than could at firſt be imagined. As a learned Man ſaith of Mr. <hi>Durham</hi>'s Lectures on the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that divers of the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Texts of that Book, which he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood little of at the beginning of his Lecture, before he cloſed his Exerciſe, were made ſo clear to him, that he thought he might well acquieſce in his Expoſition without much more debate. Though he was thus employed, yet he redeemed ſo much time for Study, that he was a General Scholar: And when there was once a ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion ſuggeſted (where there were many perſons of Quality together) that ſome of the Non-Conformiſts might be Jeſuits, (too great an honour to that Order, as if, though Learning do not die with them, yet it brings Learned Men, whom others are not on all accounts ſatisfied with, under a ſuſpicion that they belong to them) one in the Company replied, that the fitteſt perſon that he knew to make a Jeſuit, was Mr. <hi>Warren,</hi> not that he had any ſuch ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion of him, for I know he gave an high Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of him, both for Piety and Learning: But he accounted him a Perſon of ſuch quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34834:16"/>and acumen, which he gave an inſtance of in his <hi>ſo</hi> baffling a Doctor in his hearing, which was known to ſome of the Company. There are ſome living who can ſtill remember, that about fifty years agoe there was a perſon of competent Learning (as appears by a Viſitation Sermon, long ſince printed) but of greater confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that Preached a Lecture at a place in this County, wherein he took upon him to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Redemption,</hi> and ſtill after his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon he made a general challenge, as <hi>Goliah</hi> did to the Hoſt of <hi>Iſrael, Give me a man that we may fight together,</hi> 1 Sam. 17.10. He was ready to diſpute with any that ſhould queſtion what he had preached. Now there was a week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lecture not far off, where ſeveral Miniſters met, and upon conſulting together, they thought it fit for them to accept of his challenge, leſt by their ſilence they ſhould ſeem to conſent to his Doctrine, or at leaſt that (as the Hoſt of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was diſmaid and greatly afraid at the words of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liath</hi> ſo) they were afraid to encounter him; So it was agreed amongſt them to go the next Lecture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day to hear him, and to diſpute with him; and Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> was deſired to be there with them.</p>
            <p>So they went, and he made his challenge as he uſed to do; and tho' Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> was much younger than moſt of the other Miniſters, they put him upon accepting the challenge, which he did, and at the firſt on-ſet put him quite beſide his play; which did <hi>non plus</hi> him for a time; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a little while he recovered himſelf ſo far as to ask Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> a Queſtion, appealing to him, Whether he thought in his Conſcience that the interpretation which he gave of thoſe places of Scripture which he had alledged for the proof
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34834:16"/>of his Doctrine, was the true ſenſe of them; to which Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> made him preſently ſuch a reply, that he came down from the Pulpit as a man confounded, and quitted the field, came thither no more to make any further challenge. Indeed Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> did in ſome ſenſe acknowlede a general Redemption, yet not that conditional Redemption, which is contended for by ſo many Learned men; but ſuch a Redemption whereby Chriſt did obtain an Univerſal Dominion over all, ſo as not only to be the head of his Chriſt, but to be head over all things to his Church, or for their good, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.22. and whereby he had power over all fleſh that he might give eternal life to as many as the Father had given him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.2. <hi>Amyrald</hi> who was a great Abbetor of this new Hypotheſis of Redemption might (I think) ſay of it as he once did of the new Philoſophy: when two happened to come to viſit him at the ſame time, and fell into a very warm debate about the old and new Philoſophy: <hi>Amyrald</hi> after he had heard their ſeveral exceptions on one ſide and the other, crys out, <hi>difficulte pour difficulte, le vicil vaut autant que le nouveau;</hi> Difficulty for difficulty, the old is as good as the new. I doubt the new Aypotheſis of Redemption will do no more to extricate us out of pretended difficulties than the old.</p>
            <p>Some ſuppoſe that the four Beaſts mentioned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.7. are Emblems of the Miniſters of the Church; that Zeal and Courage; that Patience and Induſtriouſneſs; that Prudence in managing the Affairs of the Church; that inſight into the Myſteries of the Goſpel that ſhould be in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and which are in them in different de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, ſome excelling more in one, ſome in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34834:17"/>another. Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> did not want Courage and Patience under Affliction, ſuffering joyfully the ſpoiling of his goods, (and of his induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs I have already ſpoken) but he was Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in prudence, and inſight into the Myſteries of the Goſpel. His prudence was ſuch that he was of great uſe to his Friends in adviſing them in ſeveral Caſes, even about worldly things, though he minded them ſo little that he might ſeem to ſome to be a <hi>meer Scholar:</hi> But he was none of the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> which the Greek Comaedian complains of that were wiſe in words only, but in managing buſineſs very fools; for managing affairs he was ſo fitted, that a Conſiderable Congregation of Chriſtians of a different perſuaſion from him, would have choſen him to be a Teacher in their Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, that they might <hi>have the benefit</hi> of his preaching and of his prudence in managing the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of their Church, deſiring there might be a mutual forbearance between them in ſuch things wherein they could not be of one mind. And his writings (ſomething of which is now come out of the Preſs, and more may I hope ere long) are ſuch whereby (that I may bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Apoſtles words, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.4.) when ye Read, ye may underſtand his knowledge in the myſtery of Chriſt. He was of a very peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able temper, and did ſtudy to be quiet, and as much as in him lay to live peaceably with all men: yet would not <hi>jurare in verba magiſtri,</hi> or (in our Saviours ſenſe, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.9.) call any man Father on earth, reſigning up himſelf to him by an implicit faith. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was his antient friend, and they lived together in the ſame houſe, when Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> preached at <hi>Bridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:34834:17"/>yet when he put forth his <hi>Aphoriſms,</hi> Mr. <hi>W.</hi> being diſſatisfied with ſome things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, was his <hi>ingenious friend</hi> that he ſpeaks of in the poſtſcript to his book of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> and names in his <hi>Catholick Theology,</hi> who attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſomething at firſt, which we do not meet with indeed in his Polimical writings, becauſe Mr. <hi>W.</hi> did engage him not to draw him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a publick conteſt, by publiſhing any thing which he wrote to him: But it was that which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> did not ſlight nor anſwer <hi>unâ liturâ</hi> with one daſh, for he wrote him an anſwer to it of one and forty Sheets. To draw toward a Concluſion, he was a ſhining and burning light, and might give that for his Motto, <hi>Lucendo pereo.</hi> He waſted with giving light to others.</p>
            <p>I never heard him wiſh (with Dr. <hi>Whitaker</hi>) that he could purchaſe that health in his old age, which he empared by his night-Studies in his youth; or repent him of any pains which he had taken in his Lords work. His ſtrength fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him for ſometime before he died, ſo that he was carried to the Pulpit conſtantly (as his Predeceſſor likewiſe at <hi>Hatfield</hi> was) what a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is there betwixt looking on a Body worn out in the ſervice of mens luſts, and mourning at laſt when their body and fleſh are conſumed, and ſaying, how have I hated inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.11. and looking upon a poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed body worn out in the ſervice of Chriſt. At length more than three months before he died, his ſtrength was ſo far decayed, and his memory did ſo fail him, that he was forced quite to diſiſt from his pleaſing work, which he had taken ſo much delight in, and God did hereby make him not only willing, but deſirous
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34834:18"/>to die. Then, as one ſaid, He had <hi>vitam in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientiâ mortem in voto,</hi> was content to live in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the will of God, but having a deſire to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. As a Servant wearied with work earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires the Shadow, and as an Hireling looketh for the reward of his work, <hi>Job</hi> 7.2. This you may ſee by this paſſage in a Letter to me ſometime before he dyed, when he found his ſtrength much decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz.</hi> my inability for ſervice to God, and his dear people (whom my Soul loves) makes me weary of this world, and willing to be gone to the remaining reſt.</p>
            <p>The Lord prepare me for it, and quicken my motion towards it, and bleſs your labours who have yet time and opportunity to work in his Vineyard. As for me, my Fleſh fails, and my Heart fails: But be thou, O God! the ſtrength of my Heart, and my portion for ever. And hereby God likewiſe brought his Friends to be willing to part with him: Many years agoe when he was near to death thro' a ſore ſickneſs, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that (as it is ſaid of <hi>Peter,</hi> Acts 12.5.) Inſtant and Earneſt prayer was made of the Church unto God for him; he wiſhed that God and his People were agreed to let him go. Now his people were willing to let him go, he could be no more uſeful to them, and his ſtrength was but labour and ſorrow, having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt finiſhed the ſeventy fifth year of his age.</p>
            <p>If he had been taken away in his ſtrength, and while he was buſied in his Maſters work, how great lamentation would have been made over him? for the loſs of his publick labours which had ſo oft been ſo great a comfort and refreſhment to them, for the loſs of his prudent
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34834:18"/>Counſels, Spiritual Conſolations, ſympathy in Afflictions, pathetical and earneſt Interceſſions, and for my ſelf, I may ſay, as <hi>David</hi> for <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan,</hi> I am diſtreſſed for thee, my Brother, very pleaſant haſt thou been to me, and thy love to me was wonderful, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.26. I may without vanity ſpeak it, for when above forty years ago he ſeemed to himſelf and others to be leaving the world, he was ſpeaking to his near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Relation which was with him, of ſeveral of his friends, and when he ſpake of me, brake off abruptly only with theſe words, <hi>I loved him.</hi> Sir <hi>Fuk Grevil</hi> (afterwards Lord <hi>Brook</hi>) deſired when he dyed that he might have inſcribed on his Grave, <hi>Here lies a Friend of Sir</hi> Philip Sidney; and I ſhould think it honour enough to have it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed on mine, <hi>Here lies a Friend of</hi> Mr. War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren.</p>
            <p>I lived in intimate Friendſhip and Familiarity with him forty five years; and ſpent many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious hours with him to my great comfort and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: And if I might have my choice (as <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha</hi> had at the tranſlation of <hi>Elijah,</hi> 2 Kings 2.9.) it ſhould be that a double meaſure of the Spirit of Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> might be upon me. Yea, I ſhould account my ſelf happy if I had but his meaſure of Gifts, and Parts of Learning, Grace, Temper; How quick was he to apprehend? Of what a profound Judgment? How inquiſitive in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of Truth? How diligent to dive into the depth of things, or (as we ſay) to ſift them to the bran? of a tender Spirit, weeping, like <hi>Job,</hi> for thoſe that were in trouble, and his Soul was grieved for the poor, <hi>Job</hi> 30.25. How great a meaſure had he of that wiſdom that is from above? which is pure, peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34834:19"/>full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, without Hypocriſie, <hi>James</hi> 3.17. (if I may ſpeak impartially and unfeignedly) I never knew any in whom theſe things were more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exemplified than in him. How tender, indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and prudent an Husband and Father he was? How affectionate and faithful to his Friends, how able to adviſe them? how ready to pity them, ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathize with them, and pray for them? Thoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know that were acquainted with him, who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the want of him. For tho' I hope his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers may be anſwered, (which he made while he lived, for his Friends) now he is dead; for we pray that both our ſelves and others, whom we pray for, may find Mercy and obtain Grace to help in time of need, that an anſwer may be given in (not preſently but) as the matter requires, when it may be moſt ſuitable and ſeaſonable, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. Therefore tho' <hi>Abraham</hi> did not obtain an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer when he prayed, God remembred him ſoon enough to deliver <hi>Lot,</hi> which ſeems to be the chief thing he aimed at in his prayers, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.29. Yet many dearly miſs ſuch a Friend to go to both to ſympathize with them, and adviſe them as their condition requires; and tho' there be a reſidue of the Spirit with God, to raiſe up, and ſend forth ſuch Labourers into his Harveſt; yet the want of ſuch is much lamented, now the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt is ſo plenteous. But for the Inhabitants of <hi>Hatfield Broad-Oake, Stortford,</hi> and other his Chriſtian Friends, whom he had a continual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of in his prayers, and who have fully known his Doctrine, manner of Life, Purpoſe, Faith, Long-ſuffering, Charity, Patience, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.10. and are witneſſes how holily, and juſtly, and unblameably he behaved himſelf among them,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34834:19"/>1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. As they deſire his prayers may come up for a memorial before God; ſo let them endeavour to have theſe things always in Remembrance after his deceaſe, which he was not negligent when living to put them in mind of, 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.12, &amp;c. And which others have taken care (by publiſhing ſome of them) that they may be kept in their minds, and be followers of him, and mark them which walk ſo, as they have him for an enſample, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17. For he taught by his life as well as by his Doctrine, according to the charge which <hi>Nazianzen</hi> gives to Miniſters, not to teach at all except they teach by their Converſation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:34834:20"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books ſold by</hi> Thomas Parkhurſt, <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> Three Crowns, <hi>at the lower End of</hi> Cheapſide.</head>
            <p>A Body of Practical Divinity, conſiſting of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove one hundred ſeventy ſix Sermons on the leſſer Catechiſm, compoſed by the Reverend Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter:</hi> With a Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome Sermons on ſeveral Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. By <hi>Tho. Watſon,</hi> formerly Miniſter at St. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen's Walbrook, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Paraphraſe on the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> with Notes, doctrinal and practical. By plainneſs and brevity fitted to the Uſe of Religious Families, in their daily Reading of the Scriptures; and of the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and poorer ſort of Scholars and Miniſters, who want fuller helps. With an Advertiſement of Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties in the <hi>Revelations.</hi> By the late Reverend Mr. <hi>Rich. Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Six hundred of ſelect Hymns and Spiritual Songs collected out of the Holy Bible. Together with a Catechiſm, the <hi>Canticles,</hi> and a Catalogue of Virtuous Women. The three laſt hundred of ſelect Hymns collected out of the Pſalms of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> By <hi>William Barton,</hi> A. M. late Miniſter of St. <hi>Martins</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Spiritual Songs: Or Songs of Praiſe to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God upon ſeveral occaſions. Together with the <hi>Song of Songs,</hi> which is <hi>Solomon</hi>'s: Firſt turned, then paraphraſed in Engliſh Verſe. By <hi>John Maſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sacramental Hymns collected (chiefly) out of ſuch paſſages of the New Teſtament as contain the moſt ſuitable matter of Divine Praiſes in the
<pb facs="tcp:34834:20"/>Celebration of the Lord's Supper. To which is added one Hymn relating to Baptiſm, and another to the Miniſtry. By <hi>J. Boyſe.</hi> With ſome by other hands.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David</hi> in Metre: Newly tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and diligently compared with the Original Text, and former Tranſlations: More plain, ſmooth, and agreeable to the Text, than any here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore.</p>
            <p>Of Free Juſtification by Chriſt. Written firſt in Latine by <hi>John Fox,</hi> Author of the Book of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, againſt <hi>Oſorius,</hi> &amp;c. And now Tranſlated into Engliſh, for the benefit of thoſe who love their own Souls, and would not be miſtaken in ſo great a Point.</p>
            <p>An Earneſt Call to Family-Religion: Or a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning Family-Worſhip. Being the ſubſtance of Eighteen Sermons. Preached by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Slater,</hi> A.M. Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Ornaments for the Daughters of <hi>Zion:</hi> Or the character and happineſs of a Virtuous Woman; in a Diſcourſe which directs the Female Sex how to expreſs the <hi>Fear of God</hi> in every <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>State</hi> of their <hi>Life;</hi> and obtain both <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Bleſſedneſs. Written by <hi>Cotton Mather.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Confirming Work of Religion, and its great things made plain by their primary Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Demonſtrations; whereby the meaneſt in the Church may ſoon be made able to render a rational account of their Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi>'s Alarm: Being an account of God's moſt conſiderable Diſpenſations of Judgment and Mercy towards theſe Kingdoms, for fourteen years laſt paſt; and alſo of the ſeveral ſorts of Sins and Sinners therein; eſpecially the Murmurers againſt this Preſent Government. With an Earneſt Call
<pb facs="tcp:34834:21"/>to ſpeedy Humiliation and Reformation, and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication as the chief means of proſpering Their Majeſties Councels and Preparations. Dedicated to the King and Queen.</p>
            <p>A Family-Altar Erected to the honour of the Eternal God: Or, a ſolemn Eſſay to promote the Worſhip of God in Private Houſes: Being ſome Meditations on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.5.2.3. With the Beſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail, or Dying Parents Living Hopes for their Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Children, grounded upon the Covenant of God's Grace with Believers and their Seed. Being a ſhort Diſcourſe on 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. By <hi>Oliver Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The Goſpel-Myſtery of Sanctification opened in ſundry practical Directions, ſuited eſpecially to the caſe of thoſe who labour under the guilt and power of In dwelling ſin. To which is added a Sermon of Juſtification. By <hi>Walter Marſhall</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Death improved, and immoderate Sorrow for Deceaſed Friends and Relations reproved. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you have many Arguments againſt Immoderate Sorrow, and many profitable Leſſons which we may learn from ſuch Providences. By <hi>E. Bury,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Miniſter of Great <hi>Bolas</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> Author of the Help to Holy Walking, and the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Companion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Poor Man's Help, and Young Man's Guide: Containing, 1. Doctrinal Inſtructions for the right informing of his Judgment. 2. Practical Directions for the general courſe of his Life. 3. Particular Advices for the well-managing of every day with reference to his Natural Actions, Civil Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Neceſſary Recreations, Religious Duties, particular Prayer, Publick in the Congregation, Private in the Family, Secret in the Cloſet, Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:34834:21"/>the holy Scriptures, Hearing the Word Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Receiving the Lord's Supper. By <hi>William Burkitt,</hi> M. A. of <hi>Pembroke. Hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and now Vicar of <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and Author of the practical Diſcourſe of Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>A plain Diſcourſe about taſh and ſinful Anger, as a help for ſuch as are willing to be relieved againſt ſo ſad and too generally prevailing Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper even amongſt Profeſſors of Religion; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſubſtance of ſome Sermons Preached at <hi>Mancheſter.</hi> By <hi>Henry Newcome,</hi> M. A. and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel there, and Author of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Sickneſs.</p>
            <p>The Rod or the Sword, the preſent <hi>Dilemma</hi> of the Nations of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, argued and improved on <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.14. By a true Friend to the Proteſtant Intereſt, and the Proteſtant Government.</p>
            <p>A Preſent for ſuch as have been Sick and are recovered: Or, a Diſcourſe concerning the Good that comes out of the Evil of Affliction: Being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Sermons Preached after his being raiſed from a Bed of Languiſhing. By <hi>Nath. Vincent,</hi> M.A. and Author of the Converſion of the Soul. The true Touchſtone of Grace and Nature. Diſcourſe of Conſcience. Treatiſe of Prayer and Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some paſſages in the Holy Liſe and Death of the Late Reverend Mr. <hi>Edmund Trench,</hi> moſt of them drawn out of his own Diary. Publiſhed by <hi>Joſeph Boyſe</hi> Miniſter in <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Advice to an Only Child: Or, Excellent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to all Young Perſons, containing the ſum and ſubſtance of Experimental and Practical Divinity. Written by an Eminent and Judicious Divine, for the private uſe of an Only Child. Now made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick for the benefit of all.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34834:22"/>
            <p>An account of the Bleſſed Trinity, argued from the Nature and Perfection of the Supreme Spirit, coincident with the Scripture Doctrine, in all the Articles of the Catholick Creeds; together with its Myſtical, Foederal, and Practical Uſes in the Chriſtian Religion. By <hi>William Burrough</hi> Rector of <hi>Cheyns</hi> in <hi>Bucks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Juſtification, being the ſum of Twenty Sermons. By <hi>Walter Croſs,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>Practical Diſcourſes on Sickneſs and Recovery.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning Trouble of Mind; in three Parts. By <hi>Timothy Rogers,</hi> M.A. Alſo a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Conſolation; by the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>A Plain and Familiar Diſcourſe on the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. By Biſhop <hi>Kidder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robberts</hi> on the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vines</hi> on the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Day</hi>'s Sacramental Catechiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doolittle</hi>'s Second Part of the Diſcourſe on the Sacrament, concerning Chriſt's Sufferings.</p>
            <p>The Method of Salvation: In two Parts. 1. A Sinner's Converſion to Saving Faith in God thro' Chriſt. 2. The Progreſs of a Believer from his Converſion to his Perſection, under the Work of Sanctification. By <hi>John Warren,</hi> M. A. Sometime Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Hatfield Broad Oak</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
